## Sebastien VARRETTE, PhD

# ${\bf Research~Scientist}\\ {\bf Management,~Security~and~Performance~of~HPC~systems}$

Phone: +33(0)6 74 57 90 05 E-mail: Sebastien.Varrette@uni.lu Home page: http://varrette.gforge.uni.lu GPG Key ID: 5D08BCDD4F156AD7



Born on November 27th, 1979 (in France) Married (2004), two children (2007,2010)

Short bio: Dr. Sebastien Varrette is an experienced Research Scientist within the Parallel Computing and Optimization Group (PCOG) group led by Prof. Pascal Bouvry at the University of Luxembourg. Expert in the deployment and management of High Performance Computing (HPC) systems, he is leading since that time the development of the University's HPC platform, as well as the associated expert team of system administrators managing and supporting it. His main research interests lie in the domains of the security and performance of parallel and distributed computing platforms, such as HPC or Cloud Computing infrastructures.

TECHNICAL / MANAGEMENT High Performance Computing (HPC) , Grid, Cluster & Cloud Platforms.

EXPERTISE: I'm administrating cluster-based HPC systems since 2003 (Linux environment)

Leader of an expert team of HPC system administrator since 2008.

MAIN RESEARCH DOMAINS: Security and Evaluation of Distributed Computing Platforms

#### Education

| 2007 | Ph.D. In Computer Science, with honours (Excellent/Outstanding) University of Luxembourg (UL) & Institut National Polytechnique de Grenoble (INPG) Thesis: Security in Large Scale Distributed Systems: Authentication and Result Checking |  |
|------|--|--|
| 2003 | M.Sc. in Computer Science (Univ. de Grenoble, France) with honours (TB/First Class) Speciality: Cryptology, Security and Information Coding (CSCI), rank: 1st  |  |
| 2003 | Master's Degree in Engineering (Telecoms Ensimal, Grenoble) with honours $(B/2.1)$ Speciality: Applied Mathematics, Computer Sciences & Telecommunications rank: top 10%   |  |

## **Employment**

| 2007 - now  | Research Scientist (UL, Luxembourg)              |
|-------------|--|
| 2004 - 2007 | Research Assistant (UL, Luxembourg)              |
| 2003        | System administrator (ID-IMAG, Grenoble, France) |

#### Awards

| 2018 | IEEE ICOIN 2018: Best Paper Award       |
|------|---|
| 2014 | IEEE NSS 2014: Best Student Paper Award |

### Teaching Experience

| 2014 - now  | UL HPC Schools                             | https://hpc.uni.lu/hpc-school/        |
|-------------|--|---------------------------------------|
| 2008 - now  | Parallel & Grid Computing                  | Master MICS2 (UL)                     |
| 2004 - 2007 | Programming Techniques I                   | Bachelor I1/CUT1 (UL)                 |
|             | Advanced Programming in C, C++ and Java    | Bachelor I2 (UL)                      |
|             | System Administration and Network Security | Master CSCI2 (UJF)                    |
| 2006        | CRYPTOLOGY AND NETWORK SECURITY            | Master (Univ. of Yaoundé I, Cameroon) |

#### Participation to Ph.D Boards

| Oct. 2016  | Alban Rousset, Institut FEMTO-ST, Université de Franche-Comté. Contribution à la distribu-        |
|------------|---|
|            | tion et à la synchronisation des Systèmes Multi-Agents sur les super-calculateurs, Examinateur    |
| Sept. 2018 | Gabriele Pozzetti, University of Luxembourg   |
|            | A dual-grid multiscale approach tocfd-demcouplings for multiphase flow, Jury member               |
| Dec. 2018  | David Guyon, University of Rennes I   |
|            | Energy-efficient Cloud Elasticity for Data-driven Applications (pending exact title), Jury Member |

#### **Graduate Students Supervision**

| PostDocs.    | Alban Rousset (2016 – 2018) Large scale parallel simulation for Discrete Element Method     |  |  |
|--------------|---|--|--|
|              | Joseph Emeras (2014 – 2016) Workload Analysis and Characterization of HPC Platforms for the |  |  |
|              | Study of Virtualization Service   |  |  |
| PhD.         | ABDALLAH A.Z.A. IBRAHIM (2017 – 2019) PRESENCE: Toward a Novel Approach for Performance     |  |  |
|              | Evaluation of Mobile Cloud SaaS Web Services  |  |  |
|              | Abdoul-Wahid C. Mainassara (2017 – 2019) Large scale parallel simulation for Discrete       |  |  |
|              | Element Method  |  |  |
|              | Jakub Muszyński (2011 – 2015) Cheating-Tolerance of Parallel and Distributed Evolutionary   |  |  |
|              | Algorithms in Desktop Grids and Volunteer Computing Systems                                 |  |  |
|              | Benoît Bertholon (2010 – 2013) CertiCloud & JShadObf: Toward Integrity and Software         |  |  |
|              | Protection in Cloud Computing Platforms   |  |  |
| In addition: | 13 master and 5 bachelor students supervision for their last year project and training.     |  |  |

## Research Projects

| 2007 - now  | UL High Performance Computing (HPC), co-PI (UL cumulative contribution: 10,436,151 €)         |
|-------------|---|
| 2014 - 2018 | EU COST ACTION IC1305: Network for Sustainable Ultrascale Computing (NESUS)                   |
| 2016 - 2019 | co-PI, UL LSDEM (UL contribution: 332 k€)   |
| 2014 - 2016 | AFR PostDoc J. Emeras (Evalix; Co-Supervisor; Total/AFR contribution: 56 k€)                  |
|             | Workload Analysis & Characterization of HPC Platforms for the Study of Virtualization Service |
| 2011 - 2013 | UL EvoPerf (UL contribution: 373 k€)  |
| 2010 - 2012 | FNR CORE GreenIT (Total: 1,5 M€, FNR contribution: 432 k€)                                    |
| 2010 - 2012 | AFR PhD B. Bertholon (PHD-09-142; Scientific Advisor; Total/AFR contribution: 110 k€)         |
|             | Confidentiality and Integrity Issues over Cloud Computing Platforms                           |
| 2009 - 2013 | EU COST Action IC0804: Energy efficiency in large scale distributed systems                   |
| 2009 - 2013 | EU CoreGrid   |
| 2006 - 2008 | ANR SAFESCALE-BGPR (ANR-05-SSIA-0005; ANR contribution: 68 k€)                                |
| 2005 - now  | GRID'5000 (technical committee)   |
| 2005 - 2007 | FNR-SECOM TESEGRAD (FNR contribution: 300 k€)   |
| 2004 - 2007 | CRYPTALPES  |
| 2004 - 2006 | RAGTIME (Total: 545 k€, Rhône-Alpes Region contribution: 217 k€)                              |

#### **Professional Development**

```
IEEE Computer and Computational Intelligence society member
               Junior Autorisation à Diriquer des Recherches (ADR) granted on July, 2015
               Various editorial responsibilities
                    Reviewer for International Projects: National Science Center (Poland)
                    Reviewer for several journals and international (IEEE, ACM) conferences
                    Member of several international Technical Program Committee,
                    Organizer of various conferences, either as general, program or track chair
2018 - now
               National ICT standardization delegate: ISO/TC 307: Blockchain and DLTs
               Management committee member: advisor representing Luxembourg within PRACE
2017 - now
                (Partnership for Advanced Computing in Europe)
               Management committee member: ETP4HPC
2016 - now
                General Chair, 8th IEEE Intl. Conf. Cloud Computing Technology & Science (CloudCom'16)
2016
               Delegate representing Luxembourg in EU COST Actions IC1305 and IC0804
2009 - 2018
2009 - now
               TECHNICAL ADVISOR for LCSB and the MECO Ministry on HPC projects
                UL HPC MANAGER.
2007 - now
               Cumulative Project Investment: 10,436,151 € (as of 2018).
                    662 computing nodes, 10132 cores, R_{\text{peak}} = 346.652 \text{ TFlops}
                    201 servers (74,6% are Xen/KVM VMs)
                    NFS, GPFS/Spectrumscale, Lustre Storage (Total capacity: 9852.4 TB)
                    Management of a team of 5 expert system administrators
2007 - now
               Manager of various IT services (Gitlab @ Uni.lu, Gforge @ Uni.lu...)
2006
               EGIDE mission for 3 weeks in Cameroon (master lecture – Univ. of Yaoudé I)
```

| Publication category                                       | Quantity |
|--|----------|
| Books  | 6        |
| Magazine   | 1        |
| Book Chapters  | 11       |
| Edited Books / Proceedings                                 | 1        |
| International journals                                     | 8        |
| International conferences with proceedings and reviews     | 49       |
| (French) national conferences with proceedings and reviews | 4        |
| International conferences with reviews (no proceedings)    | 7        |
| PhD Thesis   | 1        |
| Masters Thesis   | 1        |
| Technical Reports and Presentations                        | 37       |
| Miscellaneous / Poster                                     | 1        |
| Total:   | 127      |

|   | Publish            | Papers:121        | Citations:534, Years:15 | <b>h-index:12</b> ,g-index:20 | Cites/year: 35.60             |
|---|--------------------|-------------------|-------------------------|-------------------------------|-------------------------------|
|   | or Perish          | Cites/paper: 4.41 | Cites/author: 166.46    | Papers/author: 43.62          | Query date: <b>2018-04-07</b> |
| Ì | Orbi <sup>lu</sup> | DBLP              | Google Scholar          |                               |                               |

#### Selected Publications

- [1] J.-G. Dumas, P. Lafourcade, A. Tichit, and S. Varrette. Les blockchains en 50 questions: comprendre le fonctionnement et les enjeux de cette technologie innovante. Dunod, 1er edition, September 2018. 296 pages, in French.
- [2] J.-G. Dumas, J.-L. Roch, E. Tannier, and S. Varrette. *Théorie des Codes : Compression, Cryptage et Correction*. Collection Sciences Sup. Dunod, 3rd edition, August 2018. 384 pages, in French.
- [3] J.-G. Dumas, J.-L. Roch, E. Tannier, and S. Varrette. Foundations of Coding: Compression, Encryption, Error-Correction. Wiley & Sons, February 2015. 376 pages.
- [4] A. A. Z. A. Ibrahim, M. U. Wasim, S. Varrette, and Pascal Bouvry. PRESENCE: Monitoring and Modelling the Performance Metrics of Mobile Cloud SaaS Web Services. *J. Mobile Information Systems*, 2018(1351386), August 2018. Extended journal version of our IEEE ICoin 2018 paper.
- [5] M. Guzek, S. Varrette, V. Plugaru, J. E. Pecero, and P. Bouvry. A Holistic Model of the Performance and the Energy-Efficiency of Hypervisors in an HPC Environment. *Intl. J. on Concurrency and Computation: Practice and Experience (CCPE)*, 26(15):2569–2590, October 2014.
- [6] J. Muszyński, S. Varrette, P. Bouvry, F. Seredyński, and S. U. Khan. Convergence Analysis of Evolutionary Algorithms in the Presence of Crash-Faults and Cheaters. *Intl. Journal. of Computers and Mathematics with Applications (CAMWA)*, 64(12):3805–3819, December 2012.
- [7] A. A.Z.A. Ibrahim, S. Varrette, and P. Bouvry. PRESENCE: Toward a Novel Approach for Performance Evaluation of Mobile Cloud SaaS Web Services . In *Proc. of the 32nd IEEE Intl. Conf. on Information Networking (ICOIN 2018)*, Chiang Mai, Thailand, January 2018. IEEE Computer Society. **Best Paper Award**.
- [8] J. Emeras, S. Varrette, and P. Bouvry. Amazon Elastic Compute Cloud (EC2) vs. in-House HPC Platform: a Cost Analysis. In *Proc. of the 9th IEEE Intl. Conf. on Cloud Computing (CLOUD 2016)*, San Francisco, USA, June 2016. IEEE Computer Society.
- [9] V. Plugaru, S. Varrette, and P. Bouvry. Performance Analysis of Cloud Environments on Top of Energy-Efficient Platforms Featuring Low Power Processors. In *Proc. of the 6th IEEE Intl. Conf. on Cloud Computing Technology and Science (CloudCom'14)*, Singapore, December 2014. IEEE Computer Society.
- [10] J. Muszyński, S. Varrette, J.L. Jiménez Laredo, and P. Bouvry. Exploiting the Hard-wired Vulnerabilities of Newscast via Connectivity-splitting Attack. In *Proc. of the IEEE Intl. Conf. on Network and System Security (NSS 2014)*, volume 8792 of *LNCS*, pages 152–165, Xi'an, China, October 2014. Springer Verlag. **Best Student Paper Award**.
- [11] B. Bertholon, S. Varrette, and P. Bouvry. CertiCloud: a Novel TPM-based Approach to Ensure Cloud IaaS Security. In Proc. of the 4th IEEE Intl. Conf. on Cloud Computing (CLOUD 2011), Washington DC, USA, July 2011. IEEE Computer Society.